Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov.
So, today's דף daf is קט, kuf yud tet, although we'll pick
up on the middle of קח עמוד ב. kuf yud chet amud
bet. And we're in the middle of some technical conversation about how
we know this concept of שומר shomer and יד. yad. And we
just got through learning it out from the פסוקים pesukim that speak
about something falling on seeds, and it says לכם, lachem, which the
מה mah says is also the idea of יד, yad, which is
mentioned. And also that it says a שומר shomer idea by seeds,
which tells us another idea not that it brings טומאה tumah in
and out, but that it adds to the minimum size. So we
have like one more attempt at a דרשה, drasha, and then we'll
go on for put the דרשה drasha aside and go on to
some of the specific הלכות halachot that relate to it. So we
pick up on קח עמוד ב, kuf yud chet amud bet, and
רב חביבא. Rav Chaviva. It's one, two, three, four, about ten lines
down, last two words on the line, רב חביבא אמר. Rav Chaviva
amar. רב חביבא Rav Chaviva
says,
it's after like the second asterisk on the beginning of the right
hand on of the lines. There's one line with an asterisk, another
line, and then the word אמר. רב amar Rav חביבא אמר, amar.
שאני אומר, sh'ani omer,
שאני שומר shani shomer excuse
me דנבילה de-neveilah כיון דמצי
יד כעביד, keivan d'matza yad k'avid, יד שדינן לה. yad shadinan lah.
The Gemara's question if we remember at the end of yesterday was:
if I have an extra פסוק pasuk about שומר shomer by נבילה,
neveilah, how do I know to translate it to tell me a
דין din of יד? yad? Maybe it's going to tell me a
הלכה halacha about שומר? shomer? And now he's coming and the Gemara
sort of answered it towards the end of yesterday, and now he's
coming and answering that question that no, that since that since we
know that a שומר shomer by a נבילה neveilah cannot add to
the minimum size, the only halachic function it can do is that
of the יד, yad, brings טומאה tumah in and out. And therefore
we're entitled to apply it to the laws of יד. yad. And
that tells us the idea the יד yad both brings in and
brings out. Okay. Now so that's it. That was just let's not
worry about that. That was just a wrap up of the דרשה
drasha of yesterday. Now we go on to discussing the basic הלכות
halachot that a יד yad brings טומאה tumah in and out and
when a יד yad occurs by foodstuff, it even adds to the
minimum size. So let's take a
look. מתקיף לה רב יהודה בר שמואל. Matkif lah Rav Yehuda bar
Shmuel. So רב יהודה בר שמואל Rav Yehuda bar Shmuel asks: הא
תנן, ha tenan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah. הפטמא של רימון
מצטרפת, Hapitema shel rimon tzitztarofet, והנץ שלו אינו מצטרף. v'hametz shelo eino
mitztaref. So if you look at a pomegranate, right, it has a
little bit of like a twig and there's also like a leaf,
right? So the פטמא pitem is the twig, although there is always
a question whether the פטמא pitem refers to the twig that grows
at the top or it refers to
the פטמא pitemy thing at the end of the pomegranate with the,
you know, like that?
Where does that come from? At the bottom or the top of
the pomegranate?
I don't think that's where it's connected to the branch. I think
it's the other side.
The other side, right. So there's always that question whether פטמא pitem
means the like the place where it's connected to the branch or
the stuff that grows at the end not connected to the branch,
right? By אתרוג, esrog, the פטמא pitem is not connected to the
branch. Yeah, so there is but there is a debate in the
ראשונים Rishonim whether the פטמא pitem of an אתרוג esrog refers to
what we call the פטמא pitem or whether it refers to where
it's connected to the branch.
Right, very big debate.
I would say, so certainly by אתרוג esrog we rule it's the
part that's not connected to the branch. So anyway, so yeah, the
פטמא pitem of the pomegranate and it is a question which part
it means it does connect because that's considered to be a שומר.
shomer. But the leaf does not. Now why the leaf does not
is because the way רש"י Rashi explains, and רש"י Rashi here assumes
that this is why I said it was the twig, is that
the leaf is connected to this to this פטמא, pitem, so presumably
the פטמא pitem is the twig. And therefore רש"י Rashi says that
it's a שומר על גבי שומר. shomer al gabei shomer. A שומר
shomer has to be directly on the fruit in order to be
significant, not on the שומר shomer itself. Okay. ואמאי ואמאי, V'amai v'amai,
so now he says like this. So forget everything we said, I
mean not forget but don't worry about everything we said
yesterday. Basic דרשה drasha that we know the idea of שומר shomer
is על כל זרע זרוע אשר יזרע. al kol zera zeirua asher
yizarei. A type of the seed that you take up for planting,
the shell that protects it, that combines to be considered part of
the seed. Now he says, wait. The laws of שומר shomer go
beyond that model. For example, the twig of this pomegranate or whatever
the פטמא pitem is, is a שומר. shomer. ואמאי V'amai he says,
קרי כאן על כל זרע זרוע וליכא? kari kan al kol zera
zeirua v'leika? It doesn't fit the category of זרע זרוע zera zeirua
because זרע זרוע, zera zeirua, the way we explained it, is the
way you would plant a seed with its shell on it. Okay,
but this twig is not the way you would plant a pomegranate.
I mean anyway, you wouldn't plant a pomegranate seed, I mean maybe
you would, but you certainly wouldn't plant it with the twig. You'd
probably just anyway take a shoot of and plant a tree if
you wanted to. So he's saying if you really learn it out
from the פסוק, pasuk, it should have to follow that model. And
the only thing that should constitute a שומר shomer is something that
is so intimately connected with the fruit that you would plant it
together with the fruit. But it's not true here. ועוד V'od he
says, let's go beyond that. And so, how did
we learn? Our משנה, mishna, עור הוורד והקיפה מצטרף or ha-vered ve-ha-kippa
mitztareif ולטמא טומאת
אוכלין. u-letamei tumas ochlim. So the basic way we got into the
discussion of שומר shomer was that the skin connects to the meat
to be considered the minimum size for food. מנלן, Menalan, where do
you know that? How do you know that skin connects to meat?
Meaning, if your whole concept of שומר shomer is learned from the
case of planting the seed, how do you know to apply it
to other things which are not so intimately connected, which is not
something that you would actually, like, take the thing and plant it
in the ground? How do you know for it to apply to
non-seeds? How do you know it applies even with seeds? How do
you know it applies to fruit which you don't plant with their
שומר shomer in the ground? So where do you know this? אלא
תלתא קראי כתיבי, Ela tlata kra'ei ketivi, there are really three verses
that tell you the idea of שומר shomer that allow you to
more abstract and generalize it. על כל זרע זרוע אשר יזרע, Al
kol zera zerua asher yizarei'a, it mentions the word to plant and
seed three times. So what do those three times tell you? חד
לשומר דזרעים, Chad le-shomer de-zra'im, one for the שומר shomer of a
seed, which as we said yesterday is the type of thing that
is planted together with the seed, it's very much a part of
the seed. וחד לשומר דאילנות, Ve-chad le-shomer de-ilanot, one for the שומר
shomer of fruit, which like the case of the pomegranate is something
that protects the fruit even though you don't plant it with
the fruit. ואידך לשומר בשר ביצים ודגים, Ve-idach le-shomer basar beitzim ve-dagim,
other foods which are not, you know, which don't grow from the
ground, which are like from the animal world, that those things even
maybe is even a bigger step in the concepts of שומר, shomer,
but nevertheless we're able to apply to all of those. So he's
explaining, yes, we learn שומר shomer from זרע זרוע, zera zerua, but
you need to generalize it and abstract it to get it to
apply to other cases.
Okay, so sorry, you can get אשר יזרע, asher yizarei'a, which is
talking about something agricultural and apply it to, I guess.
אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi
amar Rav, יש יד לטומאה ואין יד להכשר. yesh yad le-tumah ve-ein
yad le-hechsher. Now we get to talk about, now that we're done
with the דרשות, drashot, we get to talk about some of the
parameters. Is this concept of יד yad that you remember brings טומאה
tumah in and out, will it also work for הכשר? hechsher? Remember,
when food will only become fit to become טמא tamei after after
it's been taken from the ground and after it comes in contact
with water. So let's say the water did not touch the food.
Let's say the water only touched the twig, right? It only touched,
let's say water didn't touch the nut, but only touched the shell.
So the water doesn't have to touch the whole fruit, only part
of the fruit. But if it didn't touch the fruit at all,
just the שומר shomer or or it is that considered, or excuse
me, or just the יד, yad, excuse me, here talking about יד
yad not a שומר. shomer. So let's say, I don't know, it
didn't touch the meat, it just touched the bone on which the
meat is attached. Okay, is it enough, does it have to actually
touch the fruit or is it enough to touch the יד? yad?
So יש יד לטומאה, yesh yad le-tumah, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר רב Amar Rav. says יש יד לטומאה ואין יד
להכשר. yesh yad le-tumah ve-ein yad le-hechsher. It's just a concept about
יד, yad, it's not a, it would not apply to the concept
of הכשר. hechsher. And if the liquid just touched the יד, yad,
it would not make the food susceptible. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan
amar, ורבי יוחנן ve-Rabbi Yochanan says יש יד לטומאה ולהכשר, yesh yad
le-tumah u-le-hechsher, it applies both ways. במאי מיפלגי? Be-mai miflagi? So what's
the debate based on? איבעית אימא קרא ואיבעית אימא סברא, Iba'is eima
kra ve-iba'is eima sevara, if you want I can tell you it's
logic, if I want I can tell you it's based on the
verse. איבעית אימא קרא, Iba'is eima kra, let's start, so we'll go
in reverse order, let's say it's based on the פסוק. pasuk. מר
סבר מקרא נדרש לפניו ולא לפני פניו, Mar savar mikra nidrash le-fanav
ve-lo lifnei fanav, the פסוק pasuk can be interpreted to what immediately
precedes it but not going back two steps. ומר סבר מקרא נדרש
לפניו ולפני פניו, U-mar savar mikra nidrash le-fanav u-lifnei fanav, it can
apply back two steps. Why? What does the פסוק pasuk say? It
says וכי יותן מים על זרע ונפל מנבלתם עליו
טמא הוא לכם,
ve-chi yutan mayim al
zera ve-nafal mi-nivlatam alav tamei hu lachem, if water comes onto seeds,
which is the פסוק pasuk that tells you about הכשר, hechsher, that
makes it susceptible to טומאה, tumah, and then the carcass of one
of these animals falls on
it, טמא הוא לכם. tamei hu lachem. So לכם lachem tells us
the idea of יד. yad. So one says that only applies to
the immediate juxtaposed thing, טמא, tamei, the way it becomes טמא tamei
can come through יד. yad. It doesn't go all the way back
to the beginning of the פסוק pasuk of וכי יותן מים על
זרע, ve-chi yutan mayim al zera, which talks about liquid coming in
contact. That's the other says no, no, no, once you say the
idea of יד, yad, it can apply all the way to the
beginning of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so that's a technical question of
can we read יד yad into the beginning of the פסוק. pasuk.
איבעית אימא סברא, Iba'is eima sevara, or it's logic. מר סבר הכשר
תחלת טומאה היא, Mar savar hechsher techilas tumah hi, one says that
הכשר hechsher is the beginning of טומאה. tumah. So since the idea
of יד yad is applied to טומאה, tumah, this is part of
the world of טומאה, tumah, it is making it susceptible to become
טמא, tamei, so laws of טומאה tumah apply to it. ומר סבר
הכשר לאו תחלת טומאה היא, U-mar savar hechsher lav techilas tumah hi,
no, it's true to make it susceptible, but it's not yet like
it's begun the process of becoming טמא. tamei. Just because it's susceptible
does not mean like the process has started. Maybe there's a law
that only applies to the process and does not apply to things
that precede the process. Okay, so either way it's a pretty technical
consideration. There's no real explanation about, you know, the logic, you know,
either מר mar never said, well, once we have a concept of
יד, yad, it's like a universal concept, right? It's an idea that,
like, you're indirectly touching something, because we know sometimes doing something indirectly
doesn't count, sometimes you have to do it directly. So how do
we know that just because it applies to טומאה tumah it applies
to הכשר? hechsher? And therefore we'd have that debate. You know, one
could also explain it that the idea of טומאה tumah certainly is
normally conceived of as some type of almost metaphysical force. You know,
טומאה tumah is like you touch it, it's contagious, it's under the
roof if it's a מת, meis, you know, so there's this like
force. Then maybe even when it's not touched directly, you know, maybe
it can transfer through the יד. yad. Whereas coming in contact with
liquid and becoming susceptible isn't a force; it's just like defining that
this thing has come to a new state and that maybe needs
to affect the actual object itself. So that's the debate of whether
יד yad applies to הכשר. hechsher. Okay. Now we have another. תניא
כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Tanya kevataih de-Rabbi Yochanan. We taught like Rabbi Yochanan.
כשם שיש יד לטומאה, כך יש יד להכשר. Keshem she-yesh yad le-tumah,
kach yesh yad le-hechsher. A
very explicit ברייתא. beraita. The same way the concept of יד yad
works for טומאה, tumah, it works for הכשר. hechsher. So if liquid
comes in contact with a יד, yad, it's like it came in
contact with the fruit. וכשם שאין מקבלין טומאה אלא משינתלשו, כך אין
מקבלין הכשר אלא עד שינתלשו. U-keshem she-ein mekabbelin tumah ella mi-she-yitlashu, kach
ein mekabbelin hechsher ella ad she-yitlashu.
The same way things don't become טמא tamei when they're attached to
the tree, they also הכשר hechsher doesn't apply till they are detached
from the tree. Which obviously makes sense because if הכשר hechsher applied
when they were attached to the tree, you wouldn't even have a
concept of הכשר. hechsher. Everything in the world would be הכשר. hechsher.
Everything in the world has come in contact with water. So it
says that, okay, that's true, the same way thing- now how do
you know things don't become טמא tamei when they're attached to the
tree? So רש"י Rashi says, well, we know that logically. How do
we know it logically? Because if they did, everything would be טמא.
tamei. Why would everything be טמא? tamei? Because רש"י Rashi says there
are all of these rodents on the trees. They would make them
טמא. tamei. Of course it's a little strange. All those rodents and
bugs or whatever aren't always dead. But somehow רש"י Rashi says that
no, it would be crazy. Then you'd have to worry that everything
in the world was טמא tamei because who knows what it came
in contact when it was attached? And the תורה Torah obviously does
not work with the assumption that we have to assume that things
are טמא. tamei. So you know they don't come in contact with
טומאה tumah while they're on the tree. Of course תוספות Tosafot says
maybe the reason they're not טמא tamei when they're on the tree
is because they have not yet come in contact with water. Meaning
how the גמרא Gemara starts with the assumption that they're not טמא
tamei when they're on the tree and therefore we can also say
similarly they don't become susceptible הוכשר huchshar until they're picked. But maybe
that's exactly the reason why they're not טמא. tamei. Because the הכשר
hechsher only applies once they're picked from the tree. Okay. But either
way, that is the conclusion. And obviously if we didn't say that,
we would have to assume that everything was הוכשר huchshar and that
everything was טמא. tamei. So we actually say not that way. That
the whole concept of הכשר hechsher and the whole concept of טומאה
tumah is only once they are removed. They're not a full- just
a total part of the natural world. I do actually think, as
I think I've said before, that that's part of the explanation of
הכשר hechsher is that, you know, טומאה tumah relates to the things
that are sort of part of our human society. Not just part
of like nature in its natural state. So which is to say
the same way like vessels as opposed to it doesn't apply to
sticks and stones. It only applies to vessels once they're made into
human artifacts. So even by food, until it sort of becomes under
human control is not- so you could say, well, if I'm planting
and harvesting, it's under human control. But nevertheless, this particular fruit until
it's plucked and off the tree and under human control. And הכשר
hechsher could also be seen as part of that process of like,
you know, what do you do with your fruit? At least, you
know, you wash it and there's that sense of- that's the idea
why it has to come in contact with water. It needs to
be that out of the רצון. ratzon. It's not just by naturally
coming in contact with water. You have to want the water on
it. So there is I think that sense that טומאה tumah is
only things that are sort of part of human society. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רב. Rav אין יד. Ein
yad. Now that we've discussed whether there's יד yad for הכשר, hechsher,
we're going to discuss other הלכות halachos of יד. yad. Now the
concept of יד, yad, remember, does not add to the minimum size.
Okay. But now we're going to talk about, do you need a
minimum size in order to say יד? yad? So let's take a
look. אמר רב: אין יד לפחות מכזית, ואין שומר לפחות מכפול. Amar
Rav: Ein yad le-pachos mi-kezayis, ve-ein shomer le-pachos mi-kepul. You don't say
יד yad for something that's less than the size of a כזית,
kezayis, and you don't say a שומר, shomer, which does add to
the minimum size, but even though it adds, you need to start
with a certain minimum to begin with if the thing is less
than a פול, pol, which is like a some type of I
think a lentil bean. I don't know, does anybody have a translation?
Joe, what do they say a פול pol is? I forgot to
look it up. What?
Some type of- a
fava bean I think is the translation.
What? It's a large bean. Large bean.
Thank you. All right. Anyway, okay. Now רבי יוחנן אמר: יש יד
לפחות מכזית ויש שומר לפחות מכפול. Rabbi Yochanan amar: Yesh yad le-pachos
mi-kezayis ve-yesh shomer le-pachos mi-kepul. It does apply to smaller sizes. Now,
you understand how you could have a שומר shomer on something that's
a very small size because the whole idea of שומר shomer is
that it brings it up to the minimum size. And then the
question is, how small do you have to start with in order
to apply the laws of שומר? shomer? But what would it mean
to have a יד yad to something that is less than a
כזית, kezayis, according to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Even if you touched
the thing directly that was a כזית, kezayis, we've always been saying
that for טומאה tumah you need the size of a כביצה. ke-beitzah.
So who cares if the thing is smaller than a כזית kezayis
if you do have a יד yad or don't have a יד?
yad? There's no הלכתי halachic status to it. It's not able to
receive or transmit טומאה tumah if it's less than the size of
a כביצה. ke-beitzah. So here, רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot have two scenarios. רש"י's Rashi scenario is that here's
my- I don't know, what will we use this? Here's my יד.
yad. Okay, it's a good יד, yad, right? And it's on this
thing, although this thing looks pretty big. But anyway, this thing is
only the size of a כזית, kezayis, not big enough. But it's
let's say it's a יד yad touching I don't know a fruit,
and there's a lot of other fruits on top of it. And
all the fruits combined add up to the size- all the other
whatever they are, nuts, add up to the size of a כביצה.
ke-beitzah. So if this יד yad which only connects to this one,
which is a כזית, kezayis, if this... It works, it'll bring טומאה,
tumah, and the whole total will be a כביצה kebeitzah because everything
is in a pile and touching. תוספות Tosafos says being in a
pile and touching does not does not work for the minimum size
of טומאה. tumah. It has to really be one complete item. So
תוספות Tosafos says the scenario is that
this כזית kezayis or a little less than a כביצה kebeitzah is
attached to a larger piece of meat, let's say, but it's only
hanging on by a thread. And therefore, I can't actually visually do
that, but it's a very tenuous connection. And I have the יד
yad here. So what will happen if I try to manipulate the
כזית kezayis by the יד? yad? I'll manipulate the כזית, kezayis, but
it'll detach. So therefore the יד yad only relates to the כזית,
kezayis, it doesn't relate to the whole thing, because the whole thing
won't move by manipulating the יד. yad. So the יד yad only
relates to the כזית, kezayis, but the כזית kezayis is still connected
to everything, so you do have a minimum size. So they create
those scenarios to explain who cares if you have a יד yad
to a כזית, kezayis, you need the size of a כביצה. kebeitzah.
Okay, there's another explanation as well, which is that maybe even that
maybe the size of a כביצה kebeitzah is only to transmit טומאה,
tumah, not to receive טומאה. tumah. Anyway, we won't get into it.
So what you have though now is that we do have a
concept of יד yad and שומר. shomer. Do you need a minimum
size to begin with in order to say יד, yad, in order
to say שומר? shomer? שומר, shomer, remember, even increases the size of
what you have, but do you need a minimum size to begin
with? So רב Rav says you need a כזית kezayis by יד
yad and a פול pool for שומר, shomer, and רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan says you do not. So let's take a look.
מיתיבי, Meisivie, I'll ask you on this. ביצה עצמות Beiza atzmos ועליהם
ve'aleihem ביז חצאי זיתים. beiz chatza'ei zeisim. You have two bones that
have on them the actual meat of a dead corpse. Now remember,
if you have a כזית, kezayis, until now we've talked about a
כביצה, kebeitzah, but for a corpse you go by כזית. kezayis. And
if you have a כזית kezayis of a corpse under a roof,
it transmits טומאה. tumah. So you have these two human bones that
have on them both a half of a כזית. kezayis. הכניס ראשיהם
השני לבית. Hichnis rosheihem hasheini labayis.
The non-meat part of the bone is under a roof. והבית טמא,
Vehabayis tamei, and the roof is over them. Okay, so you get
it? You have this is the head of my this is my
roof, this is my bone, it has on it meat of a
human corpse, and it's like this, right? The roof is on top
of the bone, not on top of the meat. It's two separate
bones, each one has a half כזית. kezayis. So the principle is
because of יד, yad, the same way if I were to touch
this, I would become טמא tamei through moving it. If I'm an
אהל ohel over it and I'm here, so the אהל ohel is
like I'm now אהל ohel over this over the יד, yad, I'm
sorry I can't do that, but anyway, and therefore it's like I
am touching and the יד yad transmits the טומאה. tumah. But it's
not because there's a whole כזית, kezayis, it's two half זיתים, zeisim,
but it's two ידות, yados, so it does it. So what do
you see? You see that a יד yad works on less than
a כזית, kezayis, because it's working on two separate half זיתים zeisim
to transmit the טומאה tumah under the roof. Okay, טמא, tamei, the
person under the roof is
טמא. tamei. יהודה בן נקוסא אומר, Yehuda ben Nekusa omer, יהודה בן
נקוסא Yehuda ben Nekusa says משום רבי יעקב, mishum Rebbi Yaakov, היך
שני עצמות מצטרפין לכזית? heich shenei atzmos mitztarfin lechezayis? How can two
bones combine? So you see that it's debated. The תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma holds that the יד yad works on less than a
כזית, kezayis, and רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov says it does not. Now
actually in theory, רבי יעקב Rebbi Yaakov might even admit that in
principle it could work on less than a כזית kezayis if that
could do something by itself. Maybe he just doesn't say that you
can combine two separate things. But be that as it may, let's
assume for now that that's exactly what they debated.
What's the problem? מיתיבי. Meisivie.
Okay, so the problem is how are you going to answer it?
You don't have the how you have now of course the real
question is is that the גמרא Gemara doesn't say לימא כתנאי. leima
k'tannai. Right, this is a very strange גמרא, Gemara, not in terms
of what it's doing substantively, but in terms of its style. It's
going to quote here and it's going to quote another ברייתא Braisa
where this issue seems to be debated by תנאים, Tannaim, and normally
what the גמרא Gemara would be saying is לימא כתנאי, leima k'tannai,
let's say what the debate we just recorded is the same as
this debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Rather the גמרא Gemara says, oh wait
a minute, here's a ברייתא Braisa that there's different opinions. How do
both opinions work according to you? How do both opinions work according
to you? And in the end it more or less winds up
saying that maybe they take exactly those sides. But it is strange
that it presented as a מיתיבי meisivie since obviously it just seems
to be a straight exactly this is what the תנאים Tannaim are
debating. Did you have a question?
Just to understand, the thing that's
connecting
them is the airspace, the bones are not touching each other. Correct,
exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ורב בהאי תנא דף קכ"א
עמוד א', veRav be'hai tanna daf kuf chaf aleph amud aleph, ורב
בהאי דמי
אוקימלא. veRav be'hai dami ukimlah. What does רב Rav say the case
is talking about? אי ביד, Ei beyad, if the bone is serving
as some type of a יד yad for the meat, which it
obviously is, it helps you manipulate the meat, so קשיא רישא. kashya
reisha. It's difficult the beginning, because רב Rav says it doesn't work
on less than a כזית, kezayis, and the first opinion was that
it did work even though they were two half זיתים. zeisim. אי
בשומר, Ei beshomer, if it's a שומר, shomer, now רב Rav, remember
said that it does work on less than a כזית kezayis by
a שומר, shomer, doesn't work on less than a פול, pool, but
works on less than a כזית. kezayis. So if it's a שומר,
shomer, we can understand the first opinion. Now what's a שומר? shomer?
How is a bone on which the top of it is meat
a שומר? shomer? So רש"י Rashi says you'd have to explain the
scenarios different. If we're talking about a שומר shomer by a bone,
the bone normally can manipulate stuff on it, but it doesn't protect
stuff on it. So So what we're really talking about is the
scenario is that the marrow is the meat and the bone is
the שומר shomer around the marrow. So if that's the case that
the marrow is what is significant and the bone is a שומר
shomer and that's why it works even though it's less than a
כזית, kezayit, so קשיא סיפא. kashya seifa. So you have to what
do you do about the second opinion? The second opinion says that
it doesn't work on less than a כזית kezayit and you say
a שומר shomer does work. The גמרא Gemara says the obvious answer.
איבעית אימא Iba'it eima בשומר, beshomer, איבעית אימא iba'it eima ביד. beyad.
I could say it either way. איבעית אימא Iba'it eima ביד beyad
like the simple sense of this of this ברייתא braita that it's
talking about that the bone is a יד yad and manipulates the
meat. והוא דאמר כי יהודה בן קוסטיא. Vehu de'amar ki Yehuda ben
Kustya. He says like the second opinion. The first opinion says a
יד yad works on less than a כזית kezayit and he says
like the second opinion who says how can you say less than
a כזית kezayit it works? How can you combine it? ואיבעית אימא
בשומר Ve'iba'it eima beshomer or we're talking about a שומר shomer and
והוא דאמר כתנא קמא. Vehu de'amar ketana kama. So because it's a
שומר shomer it works on less than a כזית kezayit and that's
what the תנא קמא tana kama says. The fact that יהודה בן
קוסטיא Yehuda ben Kustya is even more strict than רב, Rav fine,
he doesn't rule like him. So basically it's saying yes, there's two
opinions here. You can't go like both opinions. So he'll go like
one of the opinions and if you read the ברייתא braita simply
then it's talking about a יד, yad, he'll go like the second
opinion that takes offense and says how can a יד yad work
on less than a כזית kezayit and that's רב Rav says. רב
Rav says a יד yad does not work on less than a
כזית. kezayit. So now the גמרא Gemara says רבי יוחנן אמר כולה
ביד. Rabbi Yochanan amar kula beyad. So and how would רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan work it out? He would obviously say that it's talking
about a יד. yad. Remember רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's okay
with him that a יד yad works on less than a כזית.
kezayit. והוא דאמר כתנא קמא Vehu de'amar ketana kama and he says
like the תנא קמא. tana kama. Okay, no big deal. Here you
have a case of simply read a יד yad less than a
כזית. kezayit. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes like the תנא קמא, tana
kama, יד yad works on these two halves זיתים zeitim and רב
Rav. goes like יהודה בן קוסטיא Yehuda ben Kustya who says no,
how could it work on less than a כזית? kezayit? Okay. תא
שמע. Ta shema. We're going to try yet again from another תוספתא
Tosefta and again it's going to seem like a straight debate of
תנאי tannai but we're going to frame it as a מיתיבי. meitivei.
Come in here. רבי יהודה אומר קולית. Rabbi Yehuda omer kulit. Now
קולית kulit is the side bone, okay, it's a very large bone.
So presumably it's also got a lot of marrow in it. We'll
talk about later. So it's reasonable to think that when we talk
about the meat we're talking about the marrow. But let's take a
look. שיש עליה כזית בשר. Sheyesh aleha kezayit basar. The problem is
that it says on it. I know. So the גמרא Gemara keeps
on playing with whether it's talking about a שומר shomer and it's
the marrow or a יד yad and it's the meat on top.
But the simple sense of all these cases it's a יד yad
and it's the meat on top. So you have this thigh bone
and on it is a כזית kezayit of בשר. basar. גוררת כולה
לטומאה. Goreret kula letuma. All of it gets pulled for טומאה, tuma,
meaning that if you even though the thigh bone is very large
and the meat is let's say, you know, very far away, but
as long as it's on the bone, you touch part of the
bone, you go ahead and you are מטמא metamei the meat. That's
if it's נבילה neveila or if it's a קדשים kodashim it was
שחט. shacht. So therefore it is serving as a יד yad for
this little meat. You touch the bone, it transfers the טומאה tuma
all the way to the meat even though it is just a
כזית. kezayit. Okay, so let's keep on going. לטומאה. Letuma. רבי יהודה
אומר קולית שיש עליה כזית בשר. Rabbi Yehuda omer kulit sheyesh aleha
kezayit basar. Just said. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, others, which is usually
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say, אפילו אין עליה אלא כפול גוררת כולה
לטומאה. afilu ein aleha ela kepol goreret kula letuma.
Even if it's not the size of כזית, kezayit, even if it's
only the size of a פול pol of this bean. So here
you have the first opinion says that for it to work as
a יד yad you need a כזית, kezayit, which works very nicely
with רב. Rav Right? רב Rav says for it to work as
a יד yad you need a כזית. kezayit. And the second opinion
says that no, you don't need a יד, yad, you only need
a פול, pol, which could work for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said you didn't need a כזית, kezayit, maybe he
would admit that at least you need a פול. pol. Let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says ורב הא במאי מוקים לה?
VeRav ha bemai mokim lah? What does רב Rav say it's talking
about? אי ביד, Ei beyad, if it's a יד, yad, קשיא סיפא.
kashya seifa. The end isn't good. He doesn't agree with אחרים, Acherim,
assuming for some reason he wants to agree with everybody. אי בשומר,
Ei beshomer, if it's a שומר, shomer, קשיא רישא. kashya reisha. Why
do you need a כזית? kezayit? רב Rav doesn't need a כזית
kezayit for a שומר. shomer. גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא ביד והוא
דאמר כרבי יהודה. Iba'it eima beyad vehu de'amar keRabbi Yehuda. So very
easy. Either it's talking about a יד yad and he says like
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the first opinion. Right? The first opinion said
a כזית kezayit and if it's talking about a יד yad that's
exactly what רב Rav says you need for a
כזית. kezayit. ואיבעית אימא Ve'iba'it eima בשומר beshomer or it's talking not
about the meat on it but the meat in it and the
bone is serving as a שומר. shomer. והוא דאמר כאחרים Vehu de'amar
ke'Acherim and that's the opinion of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
you need only the size of a פול. pol. Because רב Rav,
says for a שומר shomer you don't need the size of a
כזית, kezayit, you need the size of a פול. pol. רבי יוחנן
אמר כולה בשומר והוא דאמר כאחרים. Rabbi Yochanan amar kula beshomer vehu
de'amar ke'Acherim.
It's all talking about a שומר, shomer, the marrow in it, and
he's saying like others, which is strange. Right? The גמרא Gemara could
have said it's all talking about יד yad and he's saying like
others. Right? Because if it's a יד, yad,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
what's the
הלכה halacha by יד yad is that
you don't
need a כזית. kezayit. So fine, you don't need the כזית, kezayit,
but
maybe you need
a פול pol because
that's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
yes
it's a
יד, yad, you don't need a כזית, kezayit, I disagree
with the first opinion
you need a
כזית, kezayit, but
you
still
need
a
פול. pol. For some
reason the
גמרא Gemara wants to
say
that
he could even
say
that
it's
talking about a
שומר. shomer.
We'll see in a
minute because
the גמרא Gemara now thinks it's
a
פשט pshat that
it's
talking about a
שומר. shomer. So he's saying a שומר. shomer So if you have
the shell
around a פול, pol, he says that does not serve as a
שומר shomer or well, presumably שומר shomer. makes more sense because again,
you don't need it to protect it, it's a large bean. ומטמא
בשל קטנית, umetame beshel kitnit, but if it's other types of legumes
which are smaller, then the shell around it is serving as a
type of a
שומר.
shomer. ומפני שהן עשויות כזית? umipnei shehen asuyot kezayit?
Well, both of these are smaller. פול pol we've already said is
even smaller, it seems like, than a חצי כזית. chatzi kezayit. מפני
שרוצה במשמשן, mipnei sherotze bemishmushan,
because you want their use, at least in the case of the
קטנית, kitnit, or משמשן mishmushan might mean their manipulation, okay, that you,
you know, you manipulate the bean through the
pod. Okay.
So anyway, so what do you see? So the question is that
how does it work in the case of קטניות? kitniyot? קטניות kitniyot
is less than a פול pol and you're using this שומר. shomer
So that works according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says you
can have a שומר shomer. less than a פול, pol, but קטנית
kitnit is obviously smaller than a פול, pol, that was the whole
point of his statement, and you still have this concept of שומר.
shomer, So the גמרא Gemara says כי דאמר רב אחא בריה דרבא
דכולהו משום יד. ki de'amar Rav Acha brei deRava dekulhu mishum yad.
We're not talking about the immediate shell around it and that's working
as a שומר, shomer... we're talking about the cluster or the stick
of the cluster and it's working as a יד. yad. Which means
again, I haven't really seen this, but presumably you've got all of
the pods of a, how do the pods grow? Like do multiple
pods come from one type of like a branch? That seems to
be the... what? Well, right. I mean, I don't know, קטנית kitnit
could be like...
like a string bean. Right. You have a whole bunch of them.
Right. So that's the point. You've got a whole bunch of these
let's say string beans all coming from a branch. So he says
we're not talking about the shell around the string beans, then you're
right. Oh, by the way, the other point here is that in
the משנה Mishnah it says even if only one bean is left.
And that's how the גמרא Gemara knows we're talking about less than
a פול, pol, because there's only one let's say green bean or
string bean left, so it's... and the פול pol he says because
it's big, it does work as a שומר... shomer. it doesn't work
as a שומר. shomer. So here we're talking that something is small,
it's only one bean, and it's working. How does that work if
you say that, you know, smaller than a פול pol doesn't work?
So it says no, no, no. We're not talking about the individual
shells around the bean, we're talking about the branch that holds all
of those pods, and therefore that branch is working as a יד.
yad. Because through moving that branch, you manipulate everything. So because that's
working as a יד yad to all of those pods, so therefore
that brings טומאה tumah to all of them. How do you have
a minimum size? Because presumably you're allowed to, although this seems to
have been debated before by רש"י ותוספות, Rashi veTosafot, you're allowed to
add up all of the little beans together. Right? All of the
beans are in their pods, all connected to a thing, all the
beans together is a minimum size, that adjusts a minimum size, and
that's how they can receive טומאה, tumah, and the branch is serving
as a יד. yad.
If you just had
one pod and its one shell, then therefore if there's not a
minimum size of food in the pod, the shell can't work as
a שומר.
shomer, And then also the יד. yad.
And the יד yad wouldn't work as a יד yad if you
didn't have a minimum size. So the question here is according to
רב, Rav you don't have a minimum size food in any one
shell, and the answer is you have multiple of the shells, multiple
pods, they're all connected to a branch, so because it's multiple you
have minimum size, and we're not talking about שומר, shomer. we're talking
about יד. yad. Okay. ומהי במשמשן? umai bemishmushan? What does it mean
in sort of their,
you know, because you know, you want their sort of to in
order to be protected, so or in order to sort of manipulate
them. It's a little funny, I don't really get the difference of
the implications of this word. Apparently originally the word משמשן mishmushan meant
sort of like
to
feel them or something, so that before it meant that the pod
was protecting it from touch. And here we're saying it doesn't really
mean from touch, but it means בתשמישן. betashmishan. It means that you
use the branch to manipulate them. Okay. תא שמע, tashma, come and
hear. So we're still trying to prove is there a minimum size
for יד yad and שומר. shomer The תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tanna
d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, על כל זרע זרוע אשר יזרע, al kol zera zeroa asher
yizarea, so this is how we know the whole idea of שומר
shomer by fruit or by seeds, כדרך שבני אדם מוציאין לזריעה, kederech
shebnei adam motzi'in lizri'ah, the
way people take it out to plant. חטה בקליפתה chitah b'klipatah or
שעורה בקליפתה, se'orah b'klipatah,
a wheat in its shell and barley in its shell,
עדשים בקליפתן adashim b'klipatan and lentils in their shells. Now we have
a little bit of a problem, which is what? Here's the פסוק
pasuk talking about a one wheat in its shell, so that's less
than the size of a כזית, kezayit, it's the size of a
פול. pol. So we have the idea of a שומר shomer. in
something that's smaller than a כזית kezayit or a פול, pol, which
is a nice proof according to רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan who says
there's no minimum size for שומר. shomer? What does רב Rav do
with that? So the גמרא Gemara says what Michael took for granted
yesterday, בריה שאני. biryah sha'ani. No, if it's the whole item, and
רש"י Rashi says that will explain a lot of the other questions
earlier, at least the question before about the pods and the peas,
is that if it's the whole item that gives it, remember when
you have an entire item that gives it significance. So when do
we say you need a minimum size to say יד yad or
שומר? shomer That's like if you have like a half of a
bean, half of an apple, or what before when we were talking
about meat and we're talking about a corpse or a dead animal,
so there you don't have a בריה, biryah, so there it's just
amount of stuff. That's where you need a כזית kezayit or a
פול. pol. But when you're talking about a whole agricultural thing like
a bean or a fruit, there you do not need a minimum
size. So even רב Rav who says you need a minimum size
would not say it when you have a whole thing, and that
would have explained the case before about beans as well. Okay, so
now we are done with the debate of רב and רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan about whether there is and what is the minimum size
to say יד yad and שומר shomer for. Now, בעא רבי אושעיא,
ba'ei Rabbi Oshaya, yet another question, a lot easier once you get
out of the דרשות. drashot. Okay, דף קי"ח עמוד
ב',
daf kuf yud
chet amud bet, שני שומרים מהו שיצטרפו? shnei shomrim mahu she'yitztarfu? Let's
say you have two separate שומרים, shomrim, can they combine? So what's
the case? היכי דמי? heichi dami? אילימא בזה על גבי זה, ileima
b'zeh al gabei zeh, one שומר shomer. on top of another שומר.
shomer, So let's say a good example for this would be, I
think the walnut for example is a good example, right? The walnut
has an inner protective shell and an outer shell, right? So what
maybe that's the question, do both of those combine for the minimum
size? Even peanut. Peanut, right. So a lot of things. So do
both of those, and it's important to say both combine because the
whole idea of שומר, shomer remember, A, it's to transmit the טומאה,
tumah, so if they don't combine, the outer thing if it's not
you don't consider it a יד yad or whatever would not bring
the טומאה tumah in. Also the שומר shomer gives it a minimum
size, adds to the size. So do you count the second shell?
So אילימא בזה על גבי זה, ileima b'zeh al gabei zeh, one
on top of the other, so רש"י Rashi takes it for granted
that that can't be true. ומי איכא שומר על גבי שומר? u'mi
ika shomer al gabei shomer? Can you have one שומר shomer on
top of the other? Now logically sure, I mean you could say
חז"ל Chazal do it all the time, it's a גזירה לגזירה, gezeirah
l'gezeirah, right? Sometimes you want two protections, you know, that's why nature
created two protections in order to protect these things, that they need
a double protection. But the גמרא Gemara is about saying no, conceptually
שומר shomer. if it's going to combine to the object has to
be directly connected to the object it's protecting, can't be like a
גזירה לגזירה, gezeirah l'gezeirah, שומר לשומר shomer l'shomer would not combine to
the original object. והתנן, v'hatnan, and here's how we know it, we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי יהודה אומר שלש קליפות בבצל. Rabbi
Yehuda omer shalosh klipot b'vatzal. There are three shells of an onion.
פנימית, p'nimit, the inner shell, which רש"י Rashi says here means actually
where the onion itself begins, the first layer of the actual onion,
בין שלמה בין קדורה מצטרפת, bein shleimah bein kedurah mitztarefet,
whether it's whole or whether it has a hole in it, it
still combines to the onion because it's actually edible, it's part of
the onion itself. אמצעית, emtza'it, the middle one, which is like you
know the which is you know the which is you know I
mean when you peel an onion, right, you've got like that the
big very brownish type of shell and then afterwards there's like a
thinner shell around it, right. So that inner thinner shell, שלמה מצטרפת,
shleimah mitztarefet, if it's whole it combines because then it's serving the
function of a שומר. shomer. קדורה אינה מצטרפת, kedurah einah mitztarefet, if
it's punctured it doesn't combine to the שיעור shiur because it's no
longer serving the function of a שומר. shomer. חיצונה, chitzonah, the most
outer layer, בין כך ובין כך טהורה, bein kach u'vein kach tehorah,
either way it's טהור, tahor, it's not considered connected because it's a
shell on top of a שומר. shomer So the גמרא Gemara takes
this to be a general statement that you don't have a שומר
shomer. on a שומר. shomer I should say by the way this
same is not true about יד. yad. The idea of שומר shomer
is a concept of connecting to the fruit, the proof being that
it adds to the minimum size, so it has to be directly
connected to the fruit. But a יד yad is about manipulating. So
remember the גמרא Gemara before had as a יד yad the twig
on which the pods which had the peas were connected. So that
was two degrees removed, but nevertheless since you manipulate the actual thing
with it, that is still considered a יד yad to the thing.
Is the question connection or or the idea that if there's an
inner membrane then you don't need the outer membrane as protection?
I don't think so, I mean because first of all obviously nature,
you know, from nature you see it's used, and even if you
did it from the human perspective then you know you would have
to assess each case individually, maybe in this case... I think it's
more conceptual that even if it's functioning to protect it, it's protecting
the shell directly and not protecting the thing and therefore it becomes
a I think it's more conceptual that even if it's functioning to
protect it, it's protecting the shell directly and not protecting the thing
and therefore the concept of שומר shomer that becomes an extension of
the thing itself that can only be with the thing that most
closely is connected to it. That's the way I understand it. Or
else you would have to sort of assess each case individually. Now,
the interesting question would be though, let's say it's still functioning as
a יד, yad, meaning in my case of let's say the, you
know, like let's say the, what do you call it, the, yeah,
the nut, the walnut, so a hard outer shell is maybe not
protecting the nut, it's protecting, you know, whatever, but you still manipulate
it through that. You don't need it to manipulate that, I mean
if you didn't have that you could just pick up the walnut
itself. So it's not exactly clear to me in that case whether
it could also function as a יד, yad, but as a שומר
shomer it won't. So the Gemara's thing when you ask whether two
שומרים shomerim combine, it can't be a שומר shomer on a שומר
shomer. because we know you totally discount the second level שומר. shomer,
So that can't be the question of does it combine.
Understand, so if you have this whole onion then like this mound
dot or wherever it is, and then the פול pol is on
the outer and then the פול pol is on
the outer onion
and the whole thing is טמא, tamei, I mean טהור tahor because...
So that's the question I just asked. Whether if you say it
doesn't function as a שומר, shomer are we also saying it doesn't
function as a יד? yad? The simple sense here is that it's
not and when he says here it's טהור, tahor, בין כך ובין
כך טהורה, bein kach uvein kach tehorah, it sounds like he's saying
that it even doesn't function as a יד, yad, okay, which I
guess would mean, which raises an interesting question by a יד. yad.
By a יד yad is a יד yad because you're able to
manipulate it by it or because it makes it easier to manipulate?
You know, so I'm not exactly, so I'm not exactly sure.
And let's say something, and let's say some טומאה tumah got in
the onion and died. Yeah, then, right, if you touch the outer
part you're okay, but if you touch the inner part, right, you're
not, yeah, that's basically essentially the same thing.
Right, or if part of the onion was exposed and something got
on it and you touched it.
Right, so whether being a שומר shomer? depends on the, the shell
or the, whatever it's called,
not
being
edible itself?
It's an interesting question. Right, right. Well, if it were edible, why
would you need the concept of שומר? shomer Why wouldn't it just
be, שומר shomer doesn't make it something, doesn't do something more than
being the actual food can do, it just makes it an extension
of the original food.
Right, but then there are gray areas because let's say, you know,
you could use these shells for,
maybe you wouldn't eat them, you know, maybe you don't eat the
skin of an onion, but you could if you want to make
some soup, okay.
Right, right. I'm not sure why the שומר shomer. would require that
it not be edible. My assumption had always been that it's even
if it's, you know, even though it's not edible. If it's somewhat
edible, I can't see why it shouldn't also be considered a שומר.
shomer, It's almost, yeah.
Well, but then it wouldn't be מצטרף. mitztaref.
Right. You're saying if it was a שומר על גבי שומר, shomer
al gabi shomer, and it therefore didn't have the status of a
שומר, shomer? could it also because it's still אוכל, ochel, and become
טמא tamei in its own regards. Yeah, I don't see why not.
It's an interesting question whether אוכל ochel can do a double function.
Okay, I'll get back to you on all that. All right, so
this was, let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. I'm
like as Rachel pointed out when they tried to stump Reb Yehuda
HaNasi they asked him questions from עוקצין. Uktzin.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ותנן. u-tenan. Okay,
we just did that. Okay, so what is this question of a
double שומר? shomer So
רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, שומר אוכל שחלקו קמיבעיא ליה. shomer ochel she-chilko
ka-mibaya lei. No, no, he didn't want to know a שומר shomer,
of a שומר, shomer he wanted to know the שומר shomer, of
food, but he wanted to know what would happen if you split
it. Now the scenario would be, for example, the following, which is
let's say you've got a piece of meat and it's got the
skin on it, right, the leather on it, which is considered a
שומר, shomer, the non-edible skin, to Joe's point. And let's say now
what happens is that you cut so that the skin now is
not one contiguous piece, the skin is cut, but the meat underneath
is still combined. That's the way Tosafot describes it, it works well
the way the Gemara discusses it. So does the fact that this
piece of skin is separate from this piece of skin, or leather
let's say, and this piece of skin doesn't protect the whole piece
of meat, but it does protect the piece that's directly under it,
and this piece protects the piece that's, the part of the meat
that's directly under it. For it to be a שומר, shomer, does
it have to protect everything and be one contiguous piece, or is
it enough that combined the two שומרים shomerim do the job of
protecting the meat?
If both the skins are attached to the meat.
Both are attached to the meat. It's one piece of meat with
two parts of the skin.
Okay. So כיון דהאי לא מגין אהאי והאי לא מגין אהאי לא
מצטרף. keivan de-hai lo magin a-hai ve-hai lo magin a-hai lo mitztaref.
Do we say since this leather doesn't, you know, doesn't protect the
other part of the meat and this one doesn't protect its other
part, they don't combine. In order for it to be combined it
would have to protect everything as one unit. או דילמא, o dilma,
or do you say כיון דהאי מגין אדידיה והאי מגין אדידיה מצטרף,
keivan de-hai magin a-didei ve-hai magin a-didei mitztaref, each one protects the
meat underneath it and they do combine. תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה מטהר בשל פול ומטמא בשל קטנית,
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria metaher be-shel pol u-metamei be-shel kitnit, the Mishnah
we quoted before, that he says he's not, he doesn't have a
שומר, shomer he doesn't consider the pod of this פול pol of
the bean to be a שומר shomer because it's not necessary, but
for קטנית kitnit for other legumes it
is, מפני שרוצה במישמישן, mipnei she-rotzeh be-mishmishan, because you want use them
to, like,
you know,
to... So it's a little hard to explain exactly what that proves.
רש"י Rashi says that we're making an analogy, although obviously you could
make a difference between multiple שומרים shomrim for multiple fruits as opposed
to two half שומר shomer for one thing. Two half שומר shomer
for one thing you understand. So רש"י Rashi is saying here again
the point is is that each one, each pod does not have
enough to add to its bean to be a minimum size. So
if he's saying that you can have these pods for the single
beans, right, so the only way that would work is if you
combine multiple beans with their multiple pods, then only then are you
going to get the minimum size. So you see you can combine
multiple שומרים. shomrim. Now of course that's a big jump, meaning it's
one thing to say one piece of meat, two halves of a
שומר shomer, maybe it combines, two separate שומרים, shomrim, two separate beans,
so but that's how רש"י Rashi understands it. תוספות Tosafos has another
read which for I won't go into, but let's just at least
note the problem with רש"י's Rashi read. Anyway, so what's the גמרא's
Gemara answer? So אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא Amar Rav Acha brei
deRava בכולכא bekulcha ומשום יד. umishum yad. No, we're not talking about
a שומר, shomer, we're talking here that it's the the branch on
which all of these pods are connected and it has nothing to
do with שומר, shomer, it has to do with יד. yad. ומאי
דמשמשתן, Umai demishameshan, what does it mean they're sort of touching them?
דתשמישן Detashmishan using it. Now again this proves that יד, yad, although
it's not as powerful as שומר, shomer it only transmits טומאה, tumah,
it doesn't increase the size, but because it's not as powerful, it
doesn't have to do as much. It doesn't have to be considered
one with the object. So for example, one difference as I already
told you is you can't have a שומר shomer on a שומר
shomer, because then it's like a גזירה לגזירה. gezeirah l'gezeirah. In order
for it to be considered one with the fruit, it has to
be the original line of defense around the fruit to be considered
an extension. Also this issue about combining two halves, right, the גמרא
Gemara has no problem that you have a twig that you manipulate
multiple different things that connects to all of those different things, even
though they're somehow are because if it's manipulating all of them, that's
fine. You can have one thing that sort of manipulates multiple things,
but to be considered a shell around something and to protect it
maybe and to be one with it, maybe it has to be
a unified shell. And if we're two half shells, maybe that would
not do the job. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to say the following. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל detana d'bei
Rabbi Yishmael על כל זרע זרוע אשר יזרע, al kol zera zerua
asher yizarei, the way that people do for sowing, חטה בקליפתה chita
biklipatah ושעורה בקליפתה. use'orah biklipatah. This is very similar as you see
all the proofs from our earlier discussion. Here he used to prove
this point, עדשים בקליפתן. adashim biklipatan. The same way you take out
barley and wheat in their shells. So what's the point there? So
the point there is, so what does that prove? So again רש"י
Rashi says that what it would prove is how do you have
a minimum amount to become טמא tamei if you only have one
one you know wheat seed or what do you call it, seed,
I don't know, kernel, anyway, you only have one barley kernel, how
do you have a minimum amount? The only way you have a
minimum amount is if you have multiple wheat kernels, multiple barley kernels,
but then they all have their own שומרים. shomrim. So obviously you
see that all those שומרים shomrim are combining together even though again
רש"י Rashi is assuming that we're making the same question about multiple
different fruits. So you see that two different שומרים shomrim can combine.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא, Amar
Rav Acha brei deRava, oh I skipped it, I'm sorry, did I
skip it? No, בכולכא bekulcha ומשום יד. umishum yad. So the same
way before we said we weren't talking about a שומר, shomer we're
talking about a twig and we're talking about the יד, yad, הכא
נמי hacha nami בשדרה beshidra ומשום שומר. umishum shomer.
So here too we're talking about the row, meaning it's not exactly
the same, we're not switching to a יד yad because we can't
switch to a יד, yad, this is the whole verse we learn
the concept of שומר shomer from, but we're talking about a row
of beans. Now if you talk about the beans, I said beans,
whatever, the kernels on the actual ear, you call it an ear?
I know by corn you do, anyway, whatever, on an ear of
wheat, okay, so there he's saying that there it's not separate different
שומרים. shomrim. There every every kernel, if you would remove some of
the bottom kernels, the top kernels would fall off. So there every
kernel's sort of viability is helping to protect the other kernels. They're
all sort of, you know, they're all protecting one another. So therefore
it's every everything's שומר shomer. functions as one big unified שומר. shomer
So I mean so that's the idea.
And so we're talking about planting individual?
We are, but now we're not. The way you would plant it,
the actual scenario is is that it's the wheat still on the
stalk. And the wheat on the stalk, if you touch you take
the stalk, it's not growing in the ground anymore, you touch something
to it even with its שומר shomer it becomes טמא, tamei, but
why aren't there multiple different things here, multiple different שומרים? shomrim? Yes,
but because since everything combined on the stalk is keeping it in
its place and preventing it from falling off, it's like they're all
protecting one another and it's like it's all one big unit. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
This doesn't answer anything.
Right, well we've used it as a way of of pushing off
this proof. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. בשלמא דעילייתא צריכה
לתתייתא. Bishlama d'ila'ata tzricha l'tata'ata. I understand the top row requires the
bottom row,
but because if you remove the bottom row of kernels, the top
row will fall off. Okay, right, you know, it's like a little
like a row an ear. ear of corn, right? Okay.
אלא תתאה מאי צריכה לעילאה, Ela tata'ah mai tzericha le'ila'ah, but how
does the bottom row require the top row? So the שומר shomer
provided by the top row is not helping being שומר shomer. the
bottom, because you can remove the top row and not affect the
bottom row. So the גמרא Gemara says בחדא דרא. bechada dara. Okay,
we're not talking about multiple rows, we're talking about one row. But
one row, every sort of presence of every kernel is helping keep
the other kernel in place, so it's all functioning as one שומר.
shomer So the גמרא Gemara says ומי איכא כביצה אוכל בחדא דרא?
umi ika kebeitza ochel bechada dara? So we're still back to our
problem. We only assumed we're talking about multiple items because or else
you would not have the minimum size, you wouldn't have the כביצה.
kebeitza. So the גמרא Gemara says if all you're talking about is
one row around an ear of corn or you know an ear
of wheat or whatever it is, you're not going to get the
minimum size of an egg out of one row. So the גמרא
Gemara says yes, בחיטי דשמעון בן שטח. bechitei deShimon ben Shatach. Yes,
there were these mystical right wheat stalks of שמעון בן שטח Shimon
ben Shatach that he had that were sort of like what the
מרגלים meraglim saw when they went into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and
he had a כביצה kebeitza of food in one row. The גמרא
Gemara says אה השתא דאתית להכי, ah hashta de'atit lehachi, for accepting
those types of answers, so then חדא חיטה נמי בחיטי דשמעון בן
שטח. chada chita nami bechitei deShimon ben Shatach. You don't even have
to say we're talking about multiple you know multiple grains of wheat.
We could talk about one grain of wheat that's the size of
a כביצה kebeitza as long as we're talking about those types of
scenarios. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
גופא. gufa. Alright, let's get back to a ברייתא braita we looked
at before. So we don't really have an answer to this question
about multiple שומרים shomrim combined, although those answers did seem to be
a little stretched and it does sound a little bit that multiple
שומרים shomrim might combine. But we did have the important principle that
you don't have a שומר shomer. on top of a
שומר. shomer. גופא. gufa. שני עצמות ועליהן כחצי זית בשר הכניס ראשיהן
שניים לבית הבית מהו עליהם. shnei atzamot va'aleihen kechatzi zayit basar hichnis
rasheihen sheniyim labayit habayit mahu aleihem. So again, these two bones of
a corpse which has a half of a כזית kezayit of human
flesh on each one of them, and the non-meat part is sticking
into a house, and the house is on top of them, so
it's like if on top of the whole כזית, kezayit, the יד
yad works here with less than a כזית kezayit as we said,
and therefore the it's like a whole כזית kezayit is under the
roof and everybody in the house is טמא. tamei. הבית טמא. habayit
tamei. יודן בנו של כוסא אומר משום רבי יעקב היך שני עצמות
מצטרפין לכזית? Yudan beno shel Kusa omer mishum Rabbi Yaakov heich shnei
atzamot mitztarfin lechezayit? No, you cannot have combined two half כזיתים kezayitim
with this idea of יד, yad, presumably the way we explained it,
not as a problem of combination, but that the idea of יד
yad requires a
כזית. kezayit. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, לא שנו אלא עצם
דהוה יד אבל נימא לא הוה יד. lo shanu ela etzem dehavah
yad aval nima lo havah yad. This problem that a of a
bone, you know, or not this problem, this ability of a bone
to bring the טומאה tumah in is only by a bone, that
functions as a יד. yad. But if it was just a hair,
a hair wouldn't function as a יד. yad. By a hair you
can't manipulate something through picking up the hair unless it's you know
connected very well, normally the hair will just pull out. So therefore
a hair does not function as a יד. yad. רבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו נימא נמי הוה יד. Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu nima nami havah
yad. Even a hair functions as a יד. yad. Now that's a
little strange, how can you manipulate something through a hair? But let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara explains it. איתיביה רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש. Eitiveih Rabbi Yochanan leReish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked
ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. עור שיש עליו כזית בשר הנוגע בציב היוצא
ממנו ובשער שכנגדו טמא. or sheyesh alav kezayit basar hanogea batziv hayotzei
mimenu uvase'ar shekenegdo tamei.
Let's say you have here
skin from a cow that has a כזית kezayit of meat on
it, and that כזית kezayit is meat of a נבילה. neveilah. So
if you touch the hair that protrudes from the skin,
עור or or the שער se'ar
I'm sorry, ציב tziv is actually a string of meat. If you
touch the string of meat that protrudes from it or from a
hair that protrudes, you are טמא. tamei. So there it's very explicit
that a hair functions as a יד yad and transmits טומאה. tumah.
מאי לאו משום יד? mai lav mishum yad? Don't you see it's
functioning as a יד? yad? לא משום שומר. lo mishum shomer. No,
it's a שומר. shomer, Now if it's a שומר, shomer so who
cares? You're also admitting that it's טמא. tamei. What difference does it
make? And anyway, he says ומי איכא שומר על גבי שומר? umi
ika shomer al gabei shomer? We said before you can't have a
שומר shomer. on a שומר. shomer? So if the hair is on
the skin and the skin is on the meat, so how anyway
can you call that a שומר? shomer So the גמרא Gemara says
שחויי מחלחל. shachuyei mechalchal. Yes, you can, because the hair actually goes
through the skin all the way to the meat below. Now I
don't know, I mean what? Hair?
Well, it's a שומר shomer, if you assume that there's a hole
in the meat that the hair is filling up, it's filling up
that hole.
I mean maybe a whole layer of hair you could consider.
Well, we're going to talk about a layer in a minute. Right
now we are assuming it is strange, but first we do have
to assume that the hair goes all the way through the skin.
I don't know, when I learned, I'm trying to remember that picture
I had in my high school biology book, right, about the hair
and the follicle, but doesn't the sort of the hair go under?
I mean we have very skin a thin layer of skin, right?
I mean our meat is like right our skin is like chicken
skin, right? Not like cow skin, right? It's very thin and the
meat is right underneath. But at least for this, I think the
hair does go, the follicle does go below the skin layer into
the meat layer. I don't know if it's true for cows. Okay,
cows have a very thick layer of skin. Anyway, so he's saying
yes, it is a little strange that it's called a שומר, shomer
and but שומר shomer presumably because it's filling a hole and that's
why it's not a שומר על גבי שומר. shomer al gabei shomer.
Let's just read one more sentence about this, although I do understand
that it's a hard idea. The question. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
like this: מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב, Matkif lei Rav Achah
bar Yaakov, אלא
מעתה, ela me'ata, if you say that actually the hole where hair
goes through goes all the way through, תפילין היכי כתבינן? tefillin heichi
katvinan? He's asking that question. How you write תפילין tefillin on קלף,
klaf, right? Because it used to have hair on it, and it
would then you're saying that there really are little holes there. So
shouldn't those holes mean that you're not writing, that you're writing over
a hole and you're not writing on straight קלף? klaf?
There is no other way of doing it though.
So the גמרא Gemara says, בעינא כתיבה תמה וליכא, be'ina ketiva tama
uleika, let's see what the answer is. You need a pure writing,
a full writing, and now you're telling me it's going over holes?
So אשתמיטיתיה, ishtamiteih, he forgot, הא דאמרי במערבא, ha de'amri bema'arava, what
they say in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, כל נקב שהדיו עובר עליו
אינו נקב. kol nekev shehadio over alav eino nekev.
If even if there is a tiny hole there, if the ink
passes straight over it and it makes a continuous, you know, a
continuous ink, you know, stroke, then it's not considered a hole. It's
not whether under some microscope it's a hole. So that's not a
question.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, and if you want I could say, כולה
משום יד, kulei mishum yad, yes, the hair is functioning as a
יד, yad, but doesn't ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say that there isn't
a יד yad by hair? So, but it's כי דאמר רב אילא
kide'amra Rav Illa במלוי שבין המלואים. bimloi shebein hamlo'im. The same way
רב אילא Rav Illa says, and this is sort of what you
were saying though,
that when, this is talking, a מלוי mloi is talking about like
the hair that comes out of a wheat stalk, that when not
just one strand would be enough, but if you have the whole
bunch of strands of hair that come out of the wheat stalk,
that functions as a יד yad because you can manipulate it by
holding onto all of those strands. So he says that by wheat.
So הכא נמי, hacha nami, I'm sorry, where was I? שבין המלואים,
shebein hamlo'im, הכא נמי בנימא שבין הנימין. hacha nami binima shebein hanimim.
Here too we're talking about multiple hairs.
Not just one of them, right?
You're only touching one of them, but there are multiple hairs, so
multiple hairs can function as a יד, yad, and that's where רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would agree that hairs
function as a יד. yad. But if you only have a single
hair, you can't manipulate something through a single hair. And we'll just
read the example and then we'll end. והיכא איתמר דרב אילא, Veheicha
itmar deRav Illa, where did רב אילא Rav Illa say? אה, מלוי
שבין השיבולים, Aha, mloi shebein hashibolim, the hairs on these stalks of
wheat, מטמאין ומטמאים ואין מצטרפין, metamin umetamin ve'ein mitztarfin, function like יד,
yad, they bring טומאה tumah in and out but they don't combine,
so they don't function as a שומר but as a יד. yad.
So גמרא Gemara says, למאי, למאי חזי, lemai, lemai chazi, what can
you do with one strand of this hair from the wheat? So
אמר רב אילא, amar Rav Illa, במלוי שבין המלואים. bimloi shebein hamlo'im.
We're talking about one amongst a whole group of them, so since
there's a whole bunch of those hairs, you can use it to
manipulate, and in that case, the hair functions as a יד. yad.
So we will end with this. Okay.
Yeah.
Cultural anthropology nature of it all.